All right. This is it. It's the final countdown, the final stretch. We're going to talk about web frameworks in Python and then you are going to be a verified Python pro with a stamp of approval for me personally. So
Hopefully you're ready. We're going to use some of the concepts that we learned earlier on to work with a more advanced framework called Django.
Now, what are web frameworks? Well, web frameworks are designed to support creating applications for the web while simplifying and also abstracting away a lot of what happens under the hood.
So they're going to provide you with the plumbing so that you can focus on just building your application.
There are two really popular web frameworks and Python. One is Django. Django is fully featured. It's a high level framework for building web apps and it focuses on automating and providing as much as possible.
Many large scale sites like Instagram do run on Django and because Django provides a lot out of the box, it's considered to be quite an opinionated framework.
Django builds itself as the web framework for perfectionists with deadlines.
There's quite a bit that's included in Django. There's a database ORM which is an object relational model to make working with databases as simple as working with Python instances.
There is easy to build upon admin back end interface that makes it easy to manage your content with nice forms with validation and seeming.
There is built in user authentication. There's a template language. There's protection against common security vulnerabilities and a lot more.
And you're probably thinking, well, this all sounds great and it is great until you find yourself needing to do something that doesn't really fit in the Django paradigm. And that's when things start to get complex.
To contrast Django, there's another popular framework in Python for the web called Flask and I would say that Django and Flask share equal popularity.
Flask builds itself as a micro framework for Python. It makes it really easy to make basic back end APIs and web apps with a lot less code and a lot less configuration.
I think Flask is easier for beginners to understand and set up and it's a lot less opinionated.
The drawback is if you want to start adding some of these additional components to your app like databases, authentication and other layers.
You're going to need to use plugins or third party packages because Flask doesn't provide a lot of these for you out of the box.
If you are not into Flask or Django, you can find a long list of Python web frameworks at the link here.
And for front end integrations with Python, you're not required to use the templating that's built into either Django or Flask.
Both frameworks were very well when they're paired with modern front end technologies like React, Angular and View.
And you can learn a lot about those other frameworks on front end masters.